Okay, so today's דף *daf* is דף יוד *daf yod*, and we
pick up with the משנה mishna, *mishnah*. And this is a משנה
mishnah *mishnah* that is a sort of famous משנה Mishna? *mishnah*, not
so much related to חגיגה Chagigah, *Chaguigah* really at all, except that
it's mentioned in one sort of little section of it and sort
of gets the מסכת masechet, *masechet* into some much sort of broader
type of a discussion both in this פרק perek *perek* and as
we'll see in the next one. So let's take a look. היתר
נדרים hetter nedarim פורחים באויר *Heter Nedarim porchim ba'avir*, the ability to
annul vows. The תורה Torah. *Torah* allows for a woman's father or
husband to annul the vow, but the idea that somebody who makes
any vow can go to a sage and explain why had they
realized certain things they never would have made the vow, etc., and
then the sage can annul it, so that really is and—seems to
be coming out of nowhere as we would say. So the משנה
mishnah *mishnah* says it flies in the air, it does not have
something to support itself on, ואין להם מה שיסמכו *ve'ein lahem mah
sheyismachu*. It does not have any real verse, any real thing in
the תורה Torah *Torah* to support itself on, right? So I guess,
to keep the metaphor, to be סומך *somech* is to be sort
of, to like physically rest on something, have something support you. So
this is flying in the air without support, it has nothing to
ground it. הלכות שבת Hilchos Shabbos, חגיגות והמעילות
*Hilchos Shabbos, Chaguigot, v'hameilot*, and here's why we're mentioning it here because
of the word חגיגה Chagigahs, *Chaguigah* again. Why of all places then?
If anything this probably should have been in נדרים nedarim, *Nedarim*, but
okay, I mean, there is a cross-reference there in נזיר nazir, *Nazir*.
But anyway, okay, חגיגה Chagigah *Chaguigah* gets mentioned here. Laws of שבת
Shabbat *Shabbos*, the laws of חגיגות *Chaguigot*, you know what we're talking
with the holiday sacrifices, the יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov* sacrifices,
and laws of מעילה meilah, *Meila*, הרי הם כהררים התלויים בשערה *harei
hem kehararim hatluyim bese'ara*. Those are like mountains supported on a hair.
שהן מקרא מועט והלכות מרובות
mikra muat vehalachos merubos, *Shehen mikra muat vehalachot merubot*,
that there's not like היתר נדרים hetter nedarim *Heter Nedarim* where there's
no verse. There is a little verse, right? There are some verses,
but based on the tiny little verse you have a huge mountain,
you have many many הלכות halachos *halachot*. So these huge mountains are
supported, are being somehow suspended with a hair. So it's better than
no support I suppose, but it is being somehow but only with
a hair. Of course it's a little funny. שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* you
understand are הלכות מרובות halachot merubot, *halachot merubot*. How many הלכות halachos
*halachot* are there in חגיגה Chagigah? *Chaguigah*? I mean, you know, we've
done one פרק *perek*, hasn't been so many הלכות halachos *halachot*. So
anyway, and מעילה meilah *Meila* is huge of course based on very
little verse. No, not that it's not mentioned. The difference between נדרים
nedarim, *Nedarim* and these three is that נדרים nedarim *Nedarim* basically have
no mention. These have a tiny mention, a hair's breadth that supports
them, but the amount of הלכות halachos *halachot* that we have for
them is huge, it's like a mountain. Alright, so we'll look at
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Okay. הדינים והעבודות *Hadinim veha'avodot*, so civil laws
and עבודות *avodot* presumably are laws of the service in the Temple,
והטהרות והטמאות והעריות *vehataharot vehatme'ot veha'arayot*, and טהרה *tahara* and טומאה *tuma*
and forbidden sexual acts, יש להם מה שיסמכו *yesh lahem mah sheyismachu*.
Those have real things to support themselves on. So you have היתר
נדרים hetter nedarim? *Heter Nedarim* don't have מה שיסמכו *mah sheyismachu*, these
last set have מה שיסמכו *mah sheyismachu*, are like very well clearly
based on biblical verse, and the middle stuff is a tiny little
thing that you have a huge mountain sort of suspended in mid-air.
והן הן גופי תורה Torah *Vehen hen gufei torah* and they are
the essence of the תורה Torah. *Torah*. Now the way it's right
here it sounds like these last things are the essence of the
תורה Torah *Torah* and the earlier things are not, so the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* switches the גרסא *girsa* to הן והן גופי תורה hein
v'hein gufei Torah. *hen vehen gufei torah*, these and they, meaning whether
the stuff in the last group that are clearly based on you
know clear sort of support in biblical verse, whether the stuff in
the first group that seems to have no support in biblical verse,
it's all equally תורה Torah *Torah*. No matter how much or little
it is supported by the biblical verse. Okay, that's how the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* will read it. Let's take a look at the גמרא
Gemara, *Gemara*. תניא *Tanya*, we taught in a ברייתא *braita*. רבי אליעזר
אומר *Rebbe Eliezer omer*: יש להם מה שיסמכו *yesh lahem mah sheyismachu*.
So there's a pushback. How can you say that there's no verse
based for היתר נדרים *Heter Nedarim*? Of course there's something to rely
on, might be a hair, but there's something to rely on. שנאמר
shene'emar, *Shene'emar* as the verse says, כי יפלא ki yafli *ki yafli*
if somebody enunciates, לנדור נדר neder? נזיר nazir. *lidor neder nazir*, that's
by נזירות nezirut *nazirut*, להזיר להשם *lazir lashem*, or כי יפלא ki
yafli *ki yafli* a second time, נדר neder
בערכך *neder be'erkecha*. So the word יפלא *yafli* is sort of like
to enunciate, it specifically refers to a speech act where the act
of saying something creates an actual is considered like a legal act
and creates a reality. Anyway that's used by a נדר neder *neder*
and it's used by נזיר nazir, *nazir*. שתי פעמים *Shtei pe'amim*, so
why does it twice say it? And הפלאה *hafla* here means like
to enunciate or to say clearly. אחת הפלאה על איסור ואחת הפלאה
על היתר *Achat hafla al isur ve'achat hafla al heter*, to tell
you that the same way you can enunciate and create prohibitions by
making a נדר neder. *neder*, there could be an act of enunciation
that annuls it and that is the source of a היתר נדרים
*Heter Nedarim*. Okay, of course, you know, that's really—that's pretty weak. It
doesn't mean anything.
I understand.
So is that a hair's breadth or is it really nothing? He
at least thought it was a hair. Okay, so
רבי יהושע Rebbi Yehoshua אומר יש להם מה שיסמוכו yesh lahem mah
sheyismochu lo, asher—I'll show you where they have some support. שנאמר, shene'emar,
the verse says: אשר נשבעתי באפי, asher nishbati b'api, פסוקים תהלים, psukim
Tehillim, אם יבאון אל מנוחתי, im yevo'un el menuchati, right? So I
swore in my anger. דאפי נשבעתי, d'api nishbati, so yes, I swore
in my anger, וחזרתי בי, v'hazarti bi, since it was only a
swearing in my anger, it was not, you know, it was something
I could retract later on, it was not somehow fully binding. Okay,
so what? Well, that's the problem. So תוספות Tosfos discusses that. Okay,
yes.
So, I don't know if you want to talk about this at
all, but really what does this mean about the concept of תורה
שבעל פה? Torah Sheba'al Peh? In other words...
Well, that's obviously why it's being put out there is to speak
about that the last line of הן הן גופי תורה, hein hein
gufei Torah, that you know the sort of authority of תורה שבעל
פה Torah Sheba'al Peh is that some things really are just pure
tradition and it's not based on a verse and some things you
know are more like the last category stuff that we could normally—normally
we could accept תורה שבעל פה. Torah Sheba'al Peh. Yes, פרשת משפטים,
Parshas Mishpatim, it's very clear you have all the laws but anybody
would look at it and say okay but like the details aren't
figured out, like what exactly is כי יגח שור, ki yigach shor,
you know, like obviously you might have a—you might have a certain
degree of specificity but you know obviously there's a lot of ambiguity.
So okay I could understand that you need either an oral tradition
that has traditions of what that means or you need an authoritative
body to interpret some of those gray areas. That's the last stuff.
But the two earlier categories are very questionable. Where are they coming
from? It seems like they're making this stuff up, right? So that's
exactly the point of the משנה, mishnah. to say that it's all
equally, you know, central, it's all equally תורה.
Torah I don't see—I don't see that there is any less detail,
let's say, than some of the examples that might be in the—let's
say, the some of the—some of the...
All right, so we'll see, we'll see what the גמרא Gemara says
about these things. Okay, but היתר נדרים certainly, all the פסוקים psukim
by היתר נדרים sound like, with the exception when the husband annuls
it, if you make the vow, you're bound by it. There's not
a hint in the verse that there would be anything that could
get you out of your vow. And the Rabbis are saying there
is. Okay? And there's not—not only is there like not a hint
for it, there's like the whole—the whole sort of sense of the
פסוקים psukim is that there's no option, right? You're completely bound by
your vow. Yes.
So based on this, can a חכם chacham be מיפר meifer his
own נדר? neder Because like הקדוש ברוך הוא Hakadosh Baruch Hu is
מיפר meifer his own...
Yeah, well, okay, yeah, right. No, we don't say—not as a verse.
Okay, well, תוספות Tosfos anyway says: what do you mean, it says
אם יבאון אל מנוחתי im yevo'un el menuchati and they weren't באו
אל מנוחה, ba'u el menuchah, they didn't come to ארץ ישראל. Eretz
Yisrael. So what's that a basis for? תוספות Tosfos says, well, maybe
it means not literally the מנוחה menuchah of ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael,
maybe it means עולם הבא, olam haba, and the question of whether
דור המדבר dor hamidbar have... All right, so תוספות Tosfos deals with
that. Now you see why it's debated whether it really has anything
to rely on. Okay, anyway, but that shows you an idea that
something made in anger, made not in a right state of mind,
maybe is questionable. Again, of course, as everybody here is saying, is
that if anything maybe it says the opposite, even if it's made
in anger,
you're bound by it. Okay. רבי יצחק אומר יש להם מה שיסמוכו,
Rebbi Yitzchak omer yesh lahem mah sheyismochu, it has what to rely
on, שנאמר, shene'emar: the verse says: כל נדיב לבו, kol nediv libo,
anybody of generosity of heart, right, shall go, you know, and sort
of, you know, brings the—what they vowed to the Temple, הביאו, hevi'u,
etc. So only if your heart remains sort of together with you,
like you know, your—you maintain that sort of commitment in the heart,
you know, are you still bound by it. Again, that's pretty weak.
Okay. חנניה בן אחי רבי יהושע אומר, Chananya ben achi Rebbi Yehoshua
omer, this is interesting, חנניה Chananya the son of the brother of
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says, יש להם מה שיסמוכו שנאמר: shene'emar, נשבעתי
ואקימה לשמור משפטי צדקך. nishbati va'akayeimah lishmor mishpatei tzidkecha. I have sworn
and I will perform to observe, you
know, your—the rules—you know, your righteous rules. Now where do you see
an idea of היתר נדרים? Because you see you need a second
commitment, ואקימה. va'akayeimah. That's
not—even though it's נשבעתי, nishbati, I still need to be committed to
ואקימה, va'akayeimah, meaning that's presumably hinting to the idea that there might
be an option to say נשבעתי ולא אקימה. nishbati v'lo akayeimah. Okay,
now of course we would say that option would be if you're
violating, if you're not doing your obligations, but the גמרא Gemara says
it's a hint to the idea that there's an alternative. אמר רבי
יהודה אמר שמואל—so Amar Rebbi Yehuda amar Shmuel it's pretty question whether
you consider this, you know, the debate is: is this a hair
or is this even nothing? אמר רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda אמר שמואל—רבי
יהודה said in the name of שמואל: Shmuel: אי הוה התם, i
havah hasam, if I were there, אמינא להו דידי עדיפא מדידכו, amina
lehu didi adifa midid'chu, I would have said something better than all
of yours, שנאמר, my thing is better than theirs, because the verse
says—and this is the—this verse is the one that's always
quoted—לא יחל דברו. lo yachel devaro. It says the verse that says
if somebody makes a vow he shall not violate his words or
profane his words. הוא אינו מוחל, hu eino mochel, he cannot sort
of waive, and here's the word of מוחל mochel like to waive
like to annul
a debt, right? He cannot sort of release from the debt, from
the obligation.
אבל אחרים מוחלין לו, aval acherim mochlin lo, he cannot be מיחל
דברו, meichel devaro, other people can get him out of his obligation,
so, and that's the דרשה. drasha. Any weaker than thousands of other
דרשות? drashas? Okay, fine. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so the גמרא's Gemara,
going to like שמואל's Shmuel the best. וכולהו אית בהו פירכא לבר
מדשמואל. Vechulhu it behu pircha levar midishmuel. All those other דרשות drashot
can be challenged except for שמואל. Shmuel. דלית ליה פירכא, Deleit lei
pircha, that is not that does not have
a contradiction or
does not have a serious challenge.
איבעית אימא רבי אלעזר,
Iba'it
eima
Rabbi Elazar, if
it's like רבי אלעזר's Rabbi Elazar דרשה drasha about כי יפלא ki
yafli that it says it twice. סבירא ליה כרבי יהודה Savira lei
k'Rabbi Yehuda שאמר משום רבי טרפון, she'amar mishum Rabbi Tarfon, maybe it's
like the דרשה drasha of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda in the name
of רבי טרפון. Rabbi Tarfon. דתניא רבי יהודה אומר משום רבי טרפון,
Detanya Rabbi Yehuda omer mishum Rabbi Tarfon, לעולם אין אחד מהם נזיר,
le'olam ein echad meihem nazir, שלא ניתנה נזירות אלא להפלאה. shelo nitna
nezirut ela lehafla'ah. You have a scenario, two people are sitting on
a bench and they see a guy walking over. And ראובן Reuven
says, if that guy coming here is a נזיר, nazir. then I'm
a נזיר. nazir. And שמעון Shimon says, if that guy coming here
is not a נזיר, nazir. then I am a נזיר.
nazir, And then the guy comes over and says so now, so
obviously one of these guys, ראובן Reuven or שמעון Shimon is going
to be a נזיר. nazir. But comes along רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
in the name of רבי טרפון, Rabbi Tarfon, it says neither of
them are a נזיר. nazir Okay, no matter what this guy is.
Because since it says כי יפלא to enunciate means completely unambiguous, that
at the time you take that vow there can be no doubt
about it. So here, although anyway this is a case that you
could even say that it's objectively clear which one, somebody knows if
this guy's a נזיר, nazir. it's not even something that's dependent on
the future, right? It's not like if it rains tomorrow, which is
even more sort of not certain, more here, it's clear as soon
as
one of them says it, one of them is a נזיר. nazir
We just have to find out the facts, you know, we'll have
access to the facts later but right now there's a reality whether
that guy is a נזיר nazir which will determine which one of
them is a נזיר. nazir, Nevertheless, since it is not clear and
explicit at the moment it's enunciated, it's not a binding vow. That's
a big חידוש. chiddush. Okay, so according to that, now not everybody
agrees with that. But according to that, that's why the תורה Torah
underscores כי יפלא to enunciate meaning it has to be completely unambiguous
at the time whether those words are making, are effecting the נדר
or not, or effecting the נזירות nezirut or not. לעולם אין אחד
מהם נזיר, Le'olam ein echad meihem nazir, neither of them are a
נזיר Nazir. as opposed to other opinions that says it's a, obviously
that one of them is. שלא ניתנה נזירות אלא להפלאה, Shelo nitna
nezirut ela lehafla'ah, נזירות has to be clearly enunciated at the time
without any ambiguity about whether it's effective or not.
So that's, so it's not coming to say it's a speech act
that can annul.
איבעית אימא רבי יהושע, Iba'it eima Rabbi Yehoshua, if it's like רבי
יהושע that learns it from the פסוק pasuk אשר נשבעתי
באפי.
asher
nishbati be'api.
So דאמר הכי קאמר, de'amar hachi ka'amar, באפי נשבעתי ולא הדרנא
בי.
be'api nishbati
velo hadarna bi.
Yes, I took a vow in my anger and I can't reverse
it. Who says it means I can reverse it? Maybe it means
I can't reverse it. Okay. איבעית אימא רבי יצחק Iba'it eima Rabbi
Yitzchak that says נשבעתי ואקיימה. nishbati va'akayema. So דאמר לאפוקי מדשמואל de'amar
lafoki midishmuel I'm sorry, כל נדיב לב, kol nediv lev, that you
have to remain sort of generous of the heart, you have to
remain committed. So דאמר לאפוקי מדשמואל de'amar lafoki midishmuel to exclude שמואל.
Shmuel. דאמר שמואל, De'amar Shmuel, שמואל Shmuel says, גמר בלבו צריך שיוציא
בשפתיו. gamar belibo tzarich sheyotzi bisfatav. So that שמואל Shmuel says that
a person even if they have a commitment to a נדר in
their mind or in their heart, it's not binding until it's enunciated,
until it comes out of the lips. דהא קא משמע לן דאף
על גב דלא הוציא בשפתיו. Deha ka mashma lan de'af al gav
d'lo hotzi bisfatav. So here, נדיב לב nediv lev says maybe sometimes
even a vow in your mind is binding even without being enunciated.
So there's a whole question because no, because everybody agrees in the
vast majority of times you need to enunciate, but there might be
some small areas where it's possible even without enunciating, and that's what's
being discussed, I'm not getting into it. Okay, so that's why. So
that doesn't so איבעית אימא חנניה בן אחי רבי יהושע, Iba'it eima
Chananya ben achi Rabbi Yehoshua, how about the דרשה drasha of חנניה
בן אחי רבי יהושע Chananya ben achi Rabbi Yehoshua that says נשבעתי
ואקיימה, nishbati va'akayema, that sounds like there's a second choice, after נשבעתי
nishbati there's still a decision ואקיימה, va'akayema, there's still a presumably a
possibility not. דאמר כרב גידל אמר רב, De'amar k'Rav Gidal amar Rav,
maybe it's teaching something else, like רב גידל אמר רב. Rav Gidal
amar Rav. דאמר רב גידל אמר רב, De'amar Rav Gidal amar Rav,
מנין שנשבעים לקיים את המצוות? minayin shenishba'im lekayem et hamitzvot? How do
you know that you vow in order to do a מצווה? mitzvah?
שנאמר נשבעתי ואקיימה לשמור משפטי צדקך. Shene'emar nishbati va'akayema lishmor mishpetei tzidkecha.
I have vowed and I will and I will keep it to
observe your righteous commandments. Now what's the חידוש chiddush of שנשבעים לקיים
המצוות, shenishba'im lekayem hamitzvot, right? Why so there are several- well, right.
So first of all, you could think that you're not allowed to.
Maybe since anyway you're obligated to some degree like a not necessarily
שבועה, shvuah, maybe you're already מושבע ועומד, mushba v'omed, maybe it's not
a binding שבועה shvuah because you're already obligated. רש"י Rashi says let's
נשבעתי ואקיימה nishbati va'akayema four lines from the bottom from before the
lines get wide. רש"י Rashi says, נדקאמר ואקיימה nedeka'amar va'akayema no, that's
I'm sorry, that's the first דרשה. drasha. Later רש"י Rashi says, three
lines down in the wide lines near the end of the lines,
שנשבעים לקיים מצווה, shenishba'im lekayem mitzvah, כלומר מצווה שאדם נשבע לקיים מצווה
kol omer mitzvah she'adam nishba lekayem mitzvah כדי שימהר ויזרז לקיים. kedei
sheyimaher veyizarez lekayem. Not necessarily it's allowed, but actually you should be
doing this. This is the way to push yourself and motivate. motivate
yourself to do something. Okay, it's a מצווה. mitzvah. Now they say
one of the תרי"ג מצוות, Taryag Mitzvot, מצווה mitzvah used a little
more loosely here, but yes, you're supposed to do it. Okay, where
are we? Okay, so אלא דשמואל לית ליה פירכא, Ela dishmuel leit
lei pircha, שמואל's Shmuel idea לא יחל דברו, Lo yachel devaro, he
cannot but other people can, that there is no challenge to it.
So אמר רבא ואיתימא רב נחמן בר יצחק, Amar Rava ve-itayma Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak, היינו דאמרי אינשי, Haino de-amrei inshi, this is what
people say: טבא חדא פלפלתא חריפתא Tava chada pilpelta charifta one good
sharp peppercorn is better ממלא צנא דקרי Mimalei tzanna de-kari from a
basket full of bland gourds. Okay, so one good answer. Right, I
know. So the interesting thing is is that this is said three
times in the גמרא, Gemara every single time it's when רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda says in the name of שמואל, Shmuel, if I was
there I would have given a better explanation. And it's quite interesting
the three different times. One is about how do you know that
you can be, you can break שבת Shabbos. in order to save
a life? So there's all these explanations by the תנאים Tannaim and
then שמואל Shmuel says the one that we know that's always quoted,
וחי בהם ולא שימות בהם. Vechai bahem velo sheyamut bahem. Then there's
this question in מגילה Megilla on a much less sort of important
הלכה halacha issue about how do you know the מגילה Megilla was
written ברוח הקודש? be-ruach hakodesh? Or I gotta tell you there שמואל's
Shmuel explanation was I thought not necessarily more convincing than the others,
which was basically קיימו וקיבלו היהודים, Kiymu vekiblu HaYehudim, קיימו למטה מה
שקיבלו למעלה, Kiymu lemata ma shekiblu lemala, which sort of begs the
question of how do you know it was written ברוח הקודש be-ruach
hakodesh because I'll make a דרשה drasha that says that it means
that God affirmed it. Okay, but I mean it's not how you
know it from the פסוק, pasuk, it's because you chose to make
the דרשה drasha that way. Anyway, and this one which is the
basis of התרת נדרים, hatarat nedarim, which is the one that is
generally, oops, quoted in the הלכה halacha literature of לא יחל דברו.
Lo yachel devaro. Anyway, so the quest... it's an interesting question about
whether שמואל Shmuel actually said all three or did he just say
one of them and somehow the גמרא Gemara had three versions of
it. But the other interesting thing is is that all of these
things, you know, as Dov said before, if I... any of these
דרשות drashot work as any other דרשות, drashot, you know, that we
get elsewhere. Like we're not trying to say when the גמרא Gemara
says, "Oh, maybe I could have used the פסוק pasuk differently, so
I don't like that פסוק." pasuk. Wonderful, you could say that about
every דרשה. drasha. Maybe I could use the פסוק pasuk differently. All
we're trying to say is that it's not floating in mid-air, that
it's got a little bit of a some tiny little support. So
why are those other things not good enough to be that little
hair of support, you know, and so on? But again, we also
lose sight that after all of that, what the גמרא, Gemara you
know, we have all these תנאים Tannaim that don't want to say
that there is this thing that has absolutely no support. Right? And
that is an interesting thing, right, within like sort of תורה שבעל
פה. Torah she-be'al peh. Like we have some things, the category of
things we have of laws that really we're not even claiming in
any way connects or derives from a verse are normally the category
we call הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha lemoshe misinai. And הלכה למשה מסיני,
halacha lemoshe misinai, you know, tends to be somewhat like stand-alone types
of things, not things that like in a deep fundamental way like
התרת נדרים hatarat nedarim really, you know, undercut very explicit biblical law.
I mean it is true you sometimes have like הלכה למשה מסיני
halacha lemoshe misinai that you can do certain work in the field
during תוספת שביעית tosefet shevi'it period, and assuming that תוספת שביעית tosefet
shevi'it is דאורייתא. de-oraita. But okay, תוספת שביעית tosefet shevi'it might be
דאורייתא de-oraita but it's not explicit in the פסוקים. psukim. So you
know, so to say that you've got this category that completely limits
the תורה Torah says you must keep your vow, you must keep
your vow, you must keep your vow, oh, except if someone comes
and annuls it and that we know based on absolute no פסוק.
pasuk. Like that's like a very threatening idea. So you do understand
the pushback that that you want to see this, you know, really
as somehow derived from a verse of, even though we do have
a category of תורה שבעל פה Torah she-be'al peh that is that
is not derived from verses and not legislated, understood to be biblically
binding but not derived from verses. But that's again, that's הלכה למשה
מסיני, halacha lemoshe misinai, but we wouldn't want to be putting this
in that category. Yes, exactly. What category do we want to put
this in? This is this is a really interesting problem. It actually
is a case of rabbinic power. Right, because you need a חכם,
chacham, some... Right, that's a good point too. The whole... It's not
derived from the תורה. Torah, So it's probably not in the category
of natural law, right, or things that were given to society beforehand.
And it is totally undermining of society. Of society? Sure, somebody pledges
ten million dollars and then doesn't fulfill it. Right, which never happens
in the real world, but okay. Right, but okay. Or somebody claims
they whatever thing when they signed the note.
Right, how do you run a society
when you have oaths and then you say, "Okay," or pledges and
you say, "But you know, if I can go to somebody who
can let me out of the pledge, I'm not obligated." Right. So
most נדרים, it's a good... I you know I haven't thought about
that because most נדרים, well you're right. Most נדרים in the תורה
Torah are between a person and God like they're or if they're
a pledge they're a pledge to bring a קרבן korban let's say,
you know, or they're a pledge to become a נזיר Nazir. or
to forbid certain things on yourself, right? So but you are right
that there are those types of things as well, you're נודר noder
something to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and צדקה Tzedakah the גמרא
Gemara says making a commitment to צדקה Tzedakah is a type of
a נדר. So you are right, it has both. I wasn't thinking
of your category but your category is definitely included in it. Yeah,
it's a very good point. And it undermines society to have the
power of the court to annul a marriage let's say, doesn't it?
Yeah, but here you can all you need to do is find
one person or three people, you know, you don't need, you get
your three your pals. It's not like it's a centralized authority, right?
If it were a centralized authority I could say, oh wow, you
know, they'll they'll give they'll give some serious thought before they let
you get out of your million dollar pledge. But the point is
no, you get three of your pals and you have them. Yeah,
but you get three הדיוטות hedyotos too, you know, and you can
shop around for a חכם, Chacham, right? So it's not, if it
were a centralized authority there would at least be a response to
that, but it's not, you know. And you would also want to
have like case law and standards and things. Right, you mean an
inner integrity which you would have with a בית דין, Beis Din,
but Rabbi Linzner is saying this is not the case. Yeah, I
mean look, there are some rules about what criteria have to be
met in order to annul it but you are right, it's like
you know yes, there's a lot of outs, right? And you're not
and there's no there's no strong control. That's a very good point.
But the other point that I thought you were making also, which
is that in a way the whole idea that this is the
one thing, if you think about it, that is like the power
of תורה שבעל פה Torah SheBa'al Peh without a biblical verse is
התרת נדרים. Heter Nedarim. In a way it's like it's very much
like a paradigm, the model of התרת נדרים Heter Nedarim because what's
התרת נדרים? Heter Nedarim? Somebody's coming along and you've got something like
an existing obligation, right? And just through like my words I'm coming
along and I through my role as a חכם Chacham and an
authority, I'm releasing that obligation. Right, in a way isn't that what's
going on here with תורה שבעל פה Torah SheBa'al Peh and its
relationship to תורה שבכתב, Torah SheBichtav, right? The תורה Torah says something,
right, comes along the rabbis not even really basing themselves on a
verse and they're actually overriding it, right? So sort of what happens
in the case and you make a נדר and the חכם Chacham
who's like the rabbinic authority gets you out of it. Isn't it
the opposite? What do you mean? You have תורה שבכתב Torah SheBichtav
and תורה שבעל פה Torah SheBa'al Peh comes along and tells us
how we enact and fulfill the obligations of תורה שבכתב. Torah SheBichtav.
Here you have the case that you have an obligation and the
חכם Chacham comes along and releases you. Right, but in a way
the rabbi, yes, most of the time that's what תורה שבעל פה
Torah SheBa'al Peh is doing, but first of all very often it's
sort of saying the פסוקים psukim seem to be broad and we're
and it's more limited than they appear. And here specifically the פסוקים
psukim say you're held by your vow. The פסוקים psukim say a
person makes a vow they're held by it. The rabbis come and
say you're not held by it, right, which is sort of paralleled
or there are ways, you know, if you do something you won't
be held by it, which is parallel by the actual enactment of
that. Somebody takes the vow and he's released by a חכם, Chacham,
right? So the תורה Torah. says you're committed by a vow and
the חכם Chacham comes and says that there's a way of releasing
it. So in a way yeah, it's a very strong like model
of the power of rabbinic power. It's just going on like the
idea of bringing a situation, two guys sitting in a bar, right,
and having a bar conversation, that guy's a נזיר, it's just great
to bring it into real life. Okay. הלכות שבת, Hilchos Shabbos. I
thought you were going to say it's a great setup for a
joke, two guys come into a bar. Okay anyway, הלכות שבת. Hilchos
Shabbos So now הלכות שבת hilchos Shabbos. at least have a hair
to rely on. Now yes Rabbi Linzner doesn't he have this statement
by שמואל Shmuel about the פלפלתא pilpelta החריפתא hacharipta and רבא Rava
comes in and says yeah yeah, רבא's Rava the one. Right and
then which is רבא Rava coming after the הלכה halacha of שמואל.
Shmuel. Exactly and שמואל Shmuel was always saying גדי עדיפא מדכרא. Gedi
adifa midichra. So now we're saying there is a basis then in
the end? According to those תנאים, Tannaim, they don't want to accept
the, it's a little scary, you know, that type of a bald
statement that the rabbis just come along and make and assert something.
Okay by the way just to finish this point about the about
the what do you call it about the hairbreadth, right? In a
way that's the way התרת נדרים Heter Nedarim works, right? התרת נדרים
Heter Nedarim works is you say to somebody had you realized this
would you have still made your vow? And you keep on like
pushing until you can find that tiny little basis to say well
actually had I thought about this maybe I wouldn't have made, oh,
that's what we're going to do, we're going to find that little
opening and we're going to release you from it based on that
opening, right? So that's also like paralleling like the tiny little hint
that the תורה Torah is giving us that's giving us now the
power to say that like you know that there's this principle of
התרת נדרים. Heter Nedarim. So again like exactly what happens in the
act of התרת נדרים Heter Nedarim is paralleled in the rabbinic sort
of reading or asserting that this institution exists. We find that little
hair and we make that assertion, yes, or that little opening. It's
almost surprising like there are other things. with really intense consequences that
you try to avoid finding a case for that. Like isn't that
a pretty common logic? One more time that that like if something
is so consequential that like if you break a vow then that's
very serious. Right. So you'd want to avoid just saying that this
vow is so strict, is so rigid.
You mean so that's why the logic of התרת נדרים heter nedarim
works because we can logically say that the person wouldn't—are you saying
that's why the Rabbis want it? Yeah, okay, but normally when the
Rabbis do that like the תורה Torah all the time says, right,
מות יומת, mot yumat, right, has all these cases of execution in
the תורה, Torah and the—I mean, that's a classic example, and the
Rabbis come and say, no, it's only when there are two witnesses
and they see it exactly at the same time and they warn
the person and he says אף על פי כן af al pi
chen with תוך כדי דיבור, toch kedei dibur, da da da. Okay,
but all of that, you know, is done through, even though it
radically changes the sort of impression one gets about what the תורה
Torah. is saying in terms of the effect of those laws, it's
done through a normal process of rabbinic exegesis. Now you could say
there too it's not on the strongest supports, but better than this
which is on no support. So, you know, that's part of the
point that this really sort of shows the power of what's be—you
know, of the rabbinic power. Okay, so now we talk about הלכות
שבת. hilchos Shabbos So the laws of שבת Shabbos are mountains on
a hair, supported on a hair. So the גמרא Gemara says, מכדי
כתיבא. michdei kesiva. What do you mean it's a mountain on a
hair? It says a lot of times don't do
מלאכה. melacha. Exactly. Exactly. I have to tell you I don't really
understand the question because, yes, it says it a lot of times,
but it says the exact same things a lot of times. It
says don't do מלאכה, melacha, don't do מלאכה, melacha, don't do מלאכה.
melacha. Wonderful, so there's a lot of hair, but I don't understand
what those מלאכות melachos are, right? And there's millions of details of
those ל״ט מלאכות lamed tes melachos and the תולדות toldos and this
and that. Right. Right, exactly. At most what you have is that
it says, it says לא תבערו אש בכל משבתיכם. lo seva'aru eish
bechol moshvoseichem. Oh, and there was a person who was מקושש עצים.
mekoshesh eitzim. Okay, well I guess actually no, you know to be
honest there's also the other case where it says, right, בחריש ובקציר
תשבות. becharish uvakatzir tishbos.
So assuming they're talking about שבת. Shabbos So at least there are
a few concrete examples of what מלאכה melacha is, but nevertheless, okay,
maybe it's not a hair, maybe it's five hairs or something, but
still, you know, you have all of מסכת שבת. Masechet Shabbos. So
anyway, but that's the גמרא's Gemara question. רש״י Rashi says it's written,
רש״י Rashi reads it to mean there's a lot of פסוקים pesukim
that say don't do מלאכה. melacha.
ולא צריכא, v'lo tzericha, and then as Rabbi
Abba—like Rabbi Abba that—דאמר רבי אבא, de'amar Rabbi Abba, החופר גומא, hachofer
guma, here's an example of something that does not really have what—you
know, only a very small hair to rely on. If somebody digs
a—digs a hole on שבת Shabbos בשבת, beShabbos, ואין צריך אלא לעפרה,
ve'ein tzarich ela le'afrah, and all he needs is the dirt. He's
not trying to dig a hole. The מלאכה melacha is digging a
hole, right? But because hole is a type of an issue of
חורש, choresh, either planting or more likely בונה, boneh, you're building a
hole as a structure, you know, to store stuff in. But this
person is digging a hole, but not for the purpose of a
hole, he's just digging a hole to get the dirt out. He
wants dirt. So in that case, ואין צריך אלא לעפרה פטור, ve'ein
tzarich ela le'afrah patur,
he's exempt אלא. ela. So the גמרא Gemara says why? First let's
figure this out. כמאן? keman? רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon? דאמר מלאכה שאינה
צריכה לגופה פטור עליה. de'amar melacha she'eina tzericha legufa patur aleha. Is
this like רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon? Because this is an idea of
a מלאכה melacha that is not needed for its own purpose, but
is a mean—is really for something else, you're exempt. So here, the
purpose of the hole, the מלאכה melacha is defined as בונה, boneh,
let's assume that, building something, building a hole like a structure that
you can use. But he is not doing it for the sake
of the hole, he's doing it for the sake of the dirt.
So that's a מלאכה melacha not done for its intended purpose is
exempt. So that only works according to רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. You've
got to—according, you've got to come up with something that everybody agrees
on, because to make this משנה work. So the גמרא Gemara says
no, אפילו תימא רבי יהודה, afilu teima Rabbi Yehuda, this would even
work according to רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. התם מתקן הכא מקלקל. hasam
metaken hacha mekalkel.
When רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says that even if you did it
for the wrong intent you're still—you're still violate, that's when the result
is something that actually is constructive. Here, the result is destructive. If
you don't want a ditch in your yard, if you don't want
a storage hole in your yard, then a hole in your yard
is actually a—it makes your yard worse, not better, right, depending on
what the context is, but if you're not interested, all you need
the dirt, you don't want the hole. Not only you don't need
it, you don't want the hole. So in that case, even רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would say you're exempt because the effect is מקלקל.
mekalkel. Okay, even though the exact same thing done with a different
thing in mind for the purpose of the hole would actually be
considered a מלאכה. melacha. So ומאי כהררין התלוין בשערה? umai kehararin hateluyin
besa'ara? Why is it a mountain supported by a hair? So the
גמרא Gemara says, מלאכת מחשבת אסרה תורה, meleches machsheves asrah Torah, ומלאכת
מחשבת לא כתיבא, umeleches machsheves lo kesiva, because the logic of exempting
you is that the תורה Torah said מלאכת מחשבת, meleches machsheves,
an intentional type of an act, and—and therefore not just you intend
to do it, but like the result is something that you are—that
you have planned and you are sort of in, you know, want
the end result. And this—and but the problem is מלאכת מחשבת meleches
machsheves is—it's written by the משכן, mishkan, and we only apply it
by שבת Shabbos. because of the association of שבת Shabbos, to the
משכן, mishkan, and therefore it's a big category, and it is true,
the category of מלאכת מחשבת meleches machsheves gets you out of a
lot of things on שבת. Shabbos, Or like half of the קולות
kulos on שבת, Shabbos, you know, basically, like if you look, like
when somebody asks a שאלה shaila on שבת, Shabbat, you know, can
I do this, can I do that or whatever, and if there's
like a justification for finding a leniency, half of the time it's
either because you'll do it through אמירה לעכום, amira l'akum, have a
non-Jew do it, or you'll do it through a שינוי, shinuy, right,
or you'll do it some type of a case as אינו מתכוון
eino miskavein and מלאכת מחשבת melechet machshevet and some type of a
פטור ptor like this. So it's a huge category of exemption and
it's not clear in any biblical verse; it's based on this association
to the משכן. Mishkan. But again, this I find this גמרא Gemara
very like unsatisfactory because to me the bigger mountain that הלכות halachos.
שבת Shabbat rests, you know, is the whole 39 מלאכות melachos with
all of the תולדות tolados and all of that, which is, you
know, very not clear in the תורה. Torah. And the linking here,
you know, this type of an idea that you're only obligated if
you actually were sort of like intending for this type of a
result and not if not, okay, I'm not saying that it's פשוט,
pashut, but it's not like such a huge חידוש chiddush that we
should sort of somehow say that the act is defined when it's
in sync with your intention. And anyway, big deal that it's learned
out from the משכן. Mishkan. So we learn tons of הלכות halachot,
from associations of one category to another category. Why all of a
sudden is הררים התלויים בשערה hararim hatloyim besara because it's learned out
from the משכן? Mishkan? So I really don't understand what the problem
of the גמרא Gemara was here and why this somehow was a
more satisfactory answer. But okay, that's what happens all the time.
Yes, Nancy told me to sweep on שבת, Shabbos, I said I
didn't want to sweep, I didn't want to sweep anyway, I said
I'm not going to do it mindlessly, she said make the house
look nicer, I said תיקו. tziku.
There you go. Alright, that's using your learning for a good
purpose. Okay, גמרא Gemara says
חגיגה, Chagigah? finally what this is doing in our מסכת, again, why
it's here, who knows. חגיגה, Chagigah. מכתב כתיבה, michtav k'siva, now forget
if anything, like the תורה says וחגותם אתו חג לה׳ שבעת ימים.
vechagosem oso chag l'Adoshem shivas yamim.
And again, you could say that means just celebrate, which is what
the גמרא Gemara is going to say, but it's reasonable to interpret
it to mean to bring a קרבן korban as a means of
celebration. And the actual number of הלכות halachot about a חגיגה Chagigah
are very tiny. What הלכות do we have about חגיגה? Chagigah. What's
considered תשלומין? tashlumin? What's the minimum amount, although that might be a
דרבנן? de'rabonon? I mean, how many הלכות do we have about חגיגה?
Chagigah If you're blind, right, then learning it out from ראייה, re'iyah,
which the גמרא Gemara by the way never spelled out how it
knows to learn the exemptions of ראייה re'iyah to חגיגה. Chagigah But
okay, it's not a large number of הלכות. Maybe a little hill
based on a שערה, se'ara, but I don't know, a subatomic. Anyway,
let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. So גמרא Gemara says like
this, מכתב כתיבה, michtav k'siva, I mean come
on, that's explicit verse, it's not just a hair. No, לא צריכא
כדרב פפא דאמר לאביי, lo tzricha kecher d'amar Rav Papa l'Abaye, like
רב פפא Rav Papa says to אביי, Abaye, ממאי דהאי וחגותם אתו
חג לה׳ זביחה? mimai dehai vechagosem oso chag l'Adoshem zvichah?
How do you know when it says celebrate a holiday to God,
that means slaughtering sacrifices? דילמא חוגא חגא קאמר רחמנא, dilma choga chaga
kamar Rachmana,
maybe it just means to have a holiday, to have a lot
of rejoicing. And there was much rejoicing. So חוגא חגא קאמר רחמנא.
choga chaga kamar Rachmana. אלא מעתה דכתיב, ella mei'atah dechsiv, no,
it can't be because it says משה Moshe says to פרעה, Paroh,
ויחגו לי במדבר, veyachogu li bamidbar,
so let them have a celebration to me. הכא נמי דחוגא חגא
הוא? hacha nami dechoga chaga hu? Was all משה Moshe saying is
we want to go out and celebrate, we want to go out
and party? No, we want to bring a חג chag to God
means sacrifices. וכי תימא הכא נמי, vechisima hacha nami,
no, maybe that is what he was saying, to have a celebration
for God. דכתיב ויאמר משה גם אתה תתן בידינו זבחים ועלות, dechsiv
vayomer Moshe gam atah titein beyadeinu zvachim ve'olos,
you'll give us, you know, sacrifices, so clearly the חג chag is
a sacrifice. Using that to פרעה. Paroh. So alright, דילמא הכי קאמר
רחמנא, dilma hachi kamar Rachmana,
maybe this is what God was saying, interesting, God who was also
משה Moshe was saying, אכלו ושתו וחוגו חגא קמי. ichlu v'shasu v'chogu
chaga kamai. Yes, eat and drink and have a celebration, so it's
not exactly clear how that answers it, but רש״י Rashi basically says
this, well the celebration could obviously mean meat, eat meat, but it
doesn't necessarily mean sacrifice. And when משה Moshe is saying תתן בידינו
זבחים ועלות, titein beyadeinu zvachim ve'olos,
זבח zevach does not have to mean a sacrifice, זבח zevach can
mean something to slaughter, or not an עולה. olah. Okay, so there
was עולה, olah, but that's not what the חגיגה Chagigah. is, so
that's not relevant to our point. Okay, so anyway, maybe it just
means a celebration with meat, maybe it doesn't mean a sacrifice. So
the גמרא Gemara says no, לא סלקא דעתך דכתיב, lo salka daitach
dechsiv, the verse says ולא ילין חלב חגי עד בקר, velo yalin
chelev chagi ad boker, the fat of my חג chag shall not
sleep over till the next morning when you bring the sacrifice. So
clearly a חג chag is a type of a sacrifice. ואי סלקא
דעתך דחוגא הוא תרבא לחגא אית ליה? v'isalka daitach dechoga hu tarba
l'chaga is lei? If you think that חג chag means just a
celebration, does a celebration have fat? So what do you mean the
fat of my celebration? That wouldn't make sense; it's the fat of
my sacrifice. So the גמרא Gemara says no, דילמא הכי קאמר רחמנא,
dilma hachi kamar Rachmana, maybe this is what the תורה says, חלב
הבא בזמן חג, chelev haba b'zman chag, fats of sacrifices that are
brought during the חג. chag. לא ילין, lo yalin, don't let them
sleep over. So whatever sacrifices you bring over יום טוב and חול
המועד, Chol HaMoed, you can't let it, you know, the fat not
be burnt on the altar overnight and if the fat would stay
off the altar until the next morning. But it doesn't mean that
the חג chag is the name of a sacrifice, it just means
sacrifices brought, whatever sacrifices you bring during the חג. chag. So this
is the one הלכה halacha that's תלויה בשערה? tluya besearah? It's you
can't have the fat like... No, no, no, the תלויה בשערה tluya
besearah is the obligation of חגיגה. Chagigah, But what we're trying to
argue is is that it's not תלויה בשערה tluya besearah because חגיגה
Chagigah just by context and looking at other verses means a קרבן.
korban. Wait, why are they ever resisting? Because it's challenging that argument
that it's תלויה בשערה. tluya besearah. What do you mean it's תלויה
בשערה? tluya besearah? It says שבעת ימים תחגו shivat yamim tachogu or
ועשית חג שבועות veasita chag Shavuot and we'll see by other פסוקים
psukim that a חג chag is a קרבן. korban. No, I know,
but then how does the גמרא Gemara say it doesn't mean that?
How does it then go the other way? Because it's trying to
support the idea that it's תלויה בשערה. tluya besearah. Okay, so that's
the issue. Can you really claim that the חגיגה Chagigah, is תלויה
בשערה? tluya besearah? So let's take a look. So maybe it is
because חג chag might not have meant there a קרבן, korban, it
might mean קרבנות korbanot brought during the חג, chag, but חג chag
might mean the holiday. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. אלא
מעתה, ela me'ata, הבא בזמן חג הוא דלא ילין. haba bizman chag
hu dela yalin. No, no, the verse can't mean that. Because then
what would it be saying? Sacrifices brought during the חג, chag, they,
the fat can't sort of sleep over, you have to burn the
fat overnight. הא דכל השנה כולה ילין? ha dechol hashana kula yalin?
But other sacrifices you can let the fat stay overnight? והכתיב vehachtiv
כל הלילה עד הבוקר kol halayla ad haboker כתיב ktiv by the
עולה, olah, that all the night until the morning is when it
should be burnt. So obviously all sacrifices the fat have to be
burnt at night and not stay over until the next morning. So
obviously the verse would not just mean, oh, sacrifices of the חג
chag have a special status. So the גמרא Gemara says, no, דאי
מההוא de'i mehahu if it was just that first by the עולה,
olah, הוה אמינא הוא לעשה, hava amina hu la'asei, that that's a
positive מצוה mitzvah that you have to burn it in the, you
know, before morning. כתב רחמנא האי ktav Rachmana hai ללאו, lelav, but
then it says לא ילין חלב חגי lo yalin chelev chagi to
say there's also a negative prohibition to let the fat stay over.
But again, maybe it's only talking not about a חג chag as
a קרבן חגיגה, korban Chagigah, but קרבנות korbanot brought during the holiday.
So גמרא Gemara says ללאו כתיב קרא אחרינא. lelav ktiv kra achrina.
No, there's another verse: ולא ילין מן הבשר אשר תזבח בערב ביום
הראשון לבקר. vlo yalin min habasar asher tizbach ba'erev bayom harishon laboker.
Do not leave over from the meat that you slaughter at night
until the next morning. So you see in general there are negative
prohibitions to let the fat or the meat stay over until the
next morning. So this חלב חגי chelev chagi can't just generally mean
general sacrifices because there are פסוקים psukim about it. It must mean
there's a specific sacrifice called a חגיגה. Chagigah גמרא Gemara says no,
ודילמא לאו ולאו בשני לאוין ועשה. vedilma lav vlav bishnei lavin ve'asei.
Even so, I'll argue that you get two negative prohibitions. But again,
חלב חגי chelev chagi might not mean the קרבן חגיגה, korban Chagigah,
it could just mean generic sacrifices brought when you bring them during
the holiday. אלא ela says the גמרא Gemara fine, אתיא מדבר מדבר.
atya midbar midbar. כתיב הכא ktiv hacha ויחגו לי במדבר. veyachogu li
bamidbar. So you're right, from the verse חגיגה, Chagigah from the verse
חלב חגי, chelev chagi, you could not have necessarily learned that it
was a sacrifice, although let's face it, that's a pretty good proof
that the fat of a חג chag means that the חג chag
is a sacrifice. But the גמרא's Gemara conceding that even though that
maybe it's not, maybe it would have meant more generic fats of
sacrifices during a חג. chag. But I'll show you that the word
חג chag means a sacrifice from the following גזירה שוה. gezeira shava.
כתיב הכא ktiv hacha ויחגו לי במדבר, veyachogu li bamidbar, celebrate for
me in the מדבר, midbar, משה Moshe says to פרעה, Paroh, וכתיב
התם vachtiv hatam and it says over there in עמוס, Amos, הזבחים
ומנחה הגשתם לי במדבר. hazvachim umincha higashtem li bamidbar. Have you brought
for me right grain offerings and meat sacrifices in the wilderness? So
מה להלן זבחים, ma lehalan zvachim, the same way there it's זבחים,
zvachim, it's funny פרעה Paroh also said זבחים ועולות, zvachim veolot, but
here we assume that means sacrifices, אף כאן זבחים. af kan zvachim.
All right, so somehow from this connection to this other verse of
מדבר, midbar, we learn out that we're talking about a sacrifice. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says ומאי קרי לה תלויה בשערה? umai kari
la tluya besearah? So why is it rested on a hair? You
now have learned out that the חגיגה Chagigah? means a sacrifice. So
based on either חלב חגי chelev chagi or this connection to this
verse in עמוס. Amos. So the גמרא Gemara says no, דברי תורה
מדברי קבלה לא ילפינן. divrei Torah midivrei kabbala lo yalfinan. That's not
a real derivation because the verse in עמוס Amos is only נביאים
Nevi'im or כתובים. Ketuvim. I know, we do it all the time
but we come up with, I complain about it all the time.
All right, anyway, in principle we don't do it, even if we
violate it. So therefore, it's not really a clear derivation. Now again,
and maybe this is just the same point about שבת, Shabbos which
is that I still don't understand why it's a הר, har, meaning
it might be a שערה, searah, but I'm not sure why it's
a הר. har. There's not a lot of הלכות, you know, and
actually it says הלכות מרובות ומקרא מועט, halachot merubot umikra muat, right?
Does it say that? הלכות מרובות, halachot merubot what does it say
in the משנה? שמקרא מועט והלכות מרובות. shemikra muat vehalachot merubot. So
the גמרא Gemara does not seem to be bothered about the
הלכות מרובות part, it seems to be bothered about the מקרא מועט,
mikra muat, and therefore, you know, both by like שבת Shabbos. and
חגיגה, Chagigah it says even if there's a
lot that we learned out from, at least... got a פסוק pasuk
to begin with, right? And that seems to be, going back to
the other problem I had before by שבת, Shabbos. yes, all it
says is לא תעשה מלאכה, lo taasaseh melachah, and we learned out
a huge mountain. But the גמרא Gemara says, but if you got
an explicit פסוק pasuk to begin with, we're not
going to call that a שערה.
searah. That's an explicit פסוק, pasuk, even though what you learn out
is enormous based on that. So do we have an explicit פסוק
pasuk by שבת Shabbos, though? לא תעשה מלאכה. lo taasaseh melachah. So
the answer is no no no. But the category of מלאכת מחשבת
meleches machsheves is a category not based on a פסוק pasuk by
שבת. Shabbos, It's based on a פסוק pasuk in the משכן. Mishkan.
So the original source of it is a
not not a פסוק pasuk by שבת. shabbat So here too by
חגיגה Chagigah it's saying the same.
Here we might not have a הר har at all, but anyway,
but at least we got a פסוק. pasuk. It says וחגתם. v'chagtam.
And the גמרא Gemara says no, because the actual פסוק pasuk that
is not really so clear that it's about a קרבן. korban. So
if you don't really start from an explicit word, that allows us
to call this a שערה. searah. Dov, you had a question? Yeah,
something similar to what you're saying, but I think it's not that
so much that it's explicit or not explicit, but that it's subject
to interpretation and the Rabbis seized on that and determined of their,
they determine, the idea is that the Rabbis assumed what the interpretation
of the פסוק pasuk is here. Right, so more or less, but
that's everything. That's not just these handful. Well, it's everything, מקרא mikra
מועט והלכות מרובות, take שחיטה, shechitah, take any... I understand, but the
point of the משנה seems to be creating three categories. התרת נדרים
hetera nedarim have nothing to rely on. שבת, shabbat מעילה, meilah חגיגה
Chagigah. have, are mountains on a hair. And then the other things,
דינים, dinim, עבודה, avoda, טהרות, taharos, טומאות, tumos, those are well supported,
right? So it's like creating this taxonomy or this categorization, right? So
what? Right. So what? I think the so what is the last
line: הן והן גופי תורה. It's all equally, don't give more weight
to the last category and less to the other. We acknowledge that
there are things that are more clearly derived and things that are
less clearly derived, and it's all equally from divinely binding and תורה
and it's all equal. Don't give them different weights. And I wonder
if there's a play on words here with שערה searah if you
read it with a ש. shin. לשער lesha'er is to, to estimate
the value of, determine the value of something. Interesting, interesting. Yeah. Quick
question, just picking up on what you were earlier just saying. These
are called דברי קבלה. divrei kabbalah. When it starts things, usually called
דברי נביאים? divrei neviim? No. Actually, no. Actually, that's a very common
term that the תוספות Tosafos says דברי קבלה divrei kabbalah on it,
especially when it's referring to it in its sort of in the
way that it does not have the same legal sense. So why
it's called דברי קבלה divrei kabbalah is another discussion. But yeah, so
I don't want to get into it. There's a whole interesting discussion
about that. But anyway. Okay. מעילות, meilos, it does not mean mysticism.
Okay. Just based on what you said, talking about the equal value
of the three different categories, which intuitively should be different. Right. It
hearkens back to when they were giving categories of worth in תורה.
Right. So the learning of תורה is the highest, the learning of
גמרא Gemara is the highest. Right. And everything else and מקרא also
is, right, is like below. מידה ואינו מידה, midah ve'eino midah, right.
מידה ואינו מידה, midah ve'eino midah, which you would think to be
the opposite. Right. Right. Good point. Right. It's true that sort of
it exactly does parallel the weighting towards תורה שבעל פה Torah she-ba'al
peh regardless of how much תורה שבכתב Torah she-bi-ksav supports it. Why
חגיגה? That's the question. Because חגיגה is one of the things mentioned.
But of course, שבת, I mean there's other things that are more
obviously in this category. התרת נדרים hetera nedarim is more obviously, let's
talk about התרת נדרים, hetera nedarim, that's really like הרים התלויים בשערה.
harim hateluyim basearah. Whatever it is, it's in נזיר. I have to
check exactly how it appears in נזיר. But anyway, yeah, I don't
know why. And it's going to allow the גמרא Gemara in the
next פרק to get into some of its very, some of the
stuff that חגיגה is well known for, the talking about like מעשה
מרכבה maaseh merkavah and מעשה בראשית maaseh bereishis and so on. Also
sort of seems to be a derivation of this digression that we
start in this משנה. So you got me, I'm sure there's some
theories about this. Let's get, let's go further. מעילות. meilos. Okay, so
מעילות meilos is another thing of הרים התלויים בשערה. harim hateluyim basearah.
And מעילה meilah, is the misuse of הקדש. hekdesh. Okay, now on
the one hand, the category of מעילה meilah. is written explicitly in
the תורה. On the other hand, it's not much of a שערה.
searah. On the other hand, it is a huge הר har as
the גמרא Gemara will say. There's an enormous amount of laws. And
not only is there an enormous amount of laws, as the גמרא
gemara is going to spell out, the laws are, a lot of
the laws are actually seem, seem arbitrary and counter-intuitive. Okay. And that's
certainly true about the category of מעילה, me'ilah, and that's what the
גמרא gemara will explore. But why exactly it's a שערה searah we'll
see. So let's take a look what the גמרא gemara says. מעילות,
meilos, so the גמרא gemara says: מקרא כתיבא. mikra k'siva. Come on,
there are verses about not misusing הקדש. hekdesh. So it's not a
שערה. searah. So אמר רמי בר חמא: amar Rami bar Chama: לא
נצרכה אלא לכדתנן. lo nitzrecha ela lechidetnan. No, the point of this,
that there's only a hair, is for the following law of מעילה.
me'ilah השליח שעשה שליחותו בעל הבית מעל. hashaliach she-asah shlichuso ba'al habayis
maal. לא עשה שליחותו שליח מעל. lo asah shlichuso shaliach maal. If
the שליח shaliach does what he was sent to do... The house
owner has done מעילה, me'ilah has trespassed; and if he does not
do what he was sent to do, then the שליח. shaliach. So
what's the scenario? Scenario is I actually go into my wallet to
take out some money and I forgot that the money in my
wallet is actually הקדש hekdesh money. I had sanctified it, I had
made a donation to the בית המקדש. beit hamikdash. I forgot to
take it out of my wallet or I took the wrong wallet
and I took some money and I go ahead and I give
Michael 100 bucks and I say, or a 20 bucks I said,
Michael, go get me some, you know, go get me some apples
and bananas, okay? And I give him the 20 bucks which is
הקדש hekdesh which I didn't realize because you can only do מעילה
me'ilah in the sense of being a קרבן מעילה korban me'ilah if
it's בשוגג. beshogeg. It's another interesting הלכה. halachah. You can actually violate
במזיד bemezid but you only bring a קרבן korban if it's בשוגג
beshogeg and so on and a whole series of the הלכות of
מעילה me'ilah, depend on the בשוגג beshogeg scenario. So I unawares give
this to Michael. If Michael goes ahead and buys the apples and
bananas, he עשה שליחותו, asah shelichuto, then I was מועל mo'el because
he did what I sent him to do, he was doing, he
was essentially my arm, my agent, so it's like I spent the
הקדש hekdesh money because he was just an extension of me. If
however he says, ah, those apples and bananas don't look any good,
I'm going to instead get some like oranges and pineapples, and he
does that, then he was מועל mo'el because he's no longer an
extension of me and he's the one spending the הקדש hekdesh money.
Okay, that's the הלכה. halachah. So let's take a look. So the
גמרא gemara says, so okay, that's the הלכה, halachah, so why is
that such a hair? Why is that not like just a reasonable
thing to say? So the גמרא gemara says, וכי עשה שליחותו אמאי
מעל, vechi asah shelichuto amai ma'al, but if Michael did what he
was sent to do, why should I be מועל? mo'el? Why should
וכי זה חוטא וזה מתחייב, vechi zeh choteh vezeh mitchayev, can this
one sin and the other one be held responsible? So Michael was
the one that spent the money, how come I'm the one that
has transgressed? So היינו דקאמרי מתלוין בשערה, hainu deka'amri matluin besa'arah, that's
why it's a mountain on a hair's breadth because again, now what's
interesting here is that the גמרא gemara... is making the hair's breadth
that logically it's a hair's, there's not a strong logic to rely
on, right? Until now it has been that there's not a verse
to rely on. Here there's not a strong logic to rely on.
So the גמרא gemara... says, אמר רבא ומאי קושיא, amar rava umai
kushya, why is that difficult to understand? דילמא שאני מעילה דגמרינן חטא
חטא מתרומה.
dilma shani me'ilah degamrinan
cheit cheit mitrumah. We learn מעילה me'ilah in certain ways from תרומה.
trumah. Now תרומה, trumah, I can make Michael my שליח shaliach to
separate תרומה trumah for me. מה התם שלוחו של אדם כמותו אף
כאן שלוחו של אדם כמותו. ma hatam shlucho shel adam kemoto af
kan shlucho shel adam kemoto. The same way there he can separate
תרומה trumah for me, here where he goes ahead and spends the
money he's like me and therefore if he does what I sent
him to do it's my transgression. Now obviously there's a difference because
the taking of תרומה trumah is a legal act that I can
legally empower him to do the act, whereas the sense of violation
and transgression and being liable for a transgression, right? But again, but
that's something that the גמרא gemara says, when do we ever have
the idea that somebody else sins and you're the one held liable?
But the גמרא's gemara answer might seem to be, okay, maybe it's
bizarre, but we at least have a basis for it, the basis
is the model of תרומה. trumah. And even though normally we don't.
You could also go further and say the reason I can make
Michael a שליח shaliach to take the תרומה trumah is because the
focus is less on the act and more on the end result,
to have the actual תרומה trumah taken and therefore it doesn't really
matter does he take it or do I take it. And the
same here by the spending of the money. Although he is the
one spending the money, I was the one who caused the money
to be misspent and therefore I am the one that really did
the violation because the causing of it to be misspent, right? It's
not like he violated שבת and I'm חייב. chayav. I might have
misled him to violate שבת but what's focused there was the act
that was done. Here the focus is less the act, giving money
to a storekeeper is an act of מעילה, me’ilah, no, it was
the context and the result of it having been misspent and having
been misused. Anyway, so that's a way of understanding why he can
do it and it still be seen as mine. But the גמרא...
Gemara was close to Michael in that case that it's תרומה? trumah?
No, I don't know and he doesn't. Oh, in the when he
separates תרומה trumah yes, but in the מעילה me’ilah. case? No, I
didn't even realize it was, I took the money accidentally. It's so
everyone's making a mistake. So if he did, then the שליח shaliach
would be מועל? mo'el? If I told you that it was money,
then totally you're on your own, yeah, then yeah absolutely. Even if
you said, but don't wait, don't do that yet? Yeah, because then
you're consciously doing something you know you shouldn't be doing. Wait, why
is he guilty in that second case? When he misuses it? Because
then he's no longer an extension of me. Meaning I might have
misled him, but in
the end, what he's doing
is not seen as my act being done through him anymore. He's
doing his own thing, he's buying pineapples and oranges. But let's say
it wasn't הקדש, hekdesh, but let's say it was your money, you
sent him to the store to buy apples and bananas and he
goes and uses his discretion and he says, 'not good, I'm going
to buy the pineapples and oranges instead'. Is he liable to you
in that case? To pay me back the money? Yeah, I mean
in that case the גמרא... Gemara what? What's your happy ending there?
Well, yeah, I mean so the גמרא Gemara discusses scenarios like that
but the basic point, the basic answer is yes, the basic answer
is so yeah, okay, so let's take a look. So the גמרא
Gemara. says אלא אמר רבא, ela amar rava, okay so in that
case... Actually makes sense. אלא אמר רבא. Ella amar Rava. Okay, so
in that case actually makes sense. לא נצרכא אלא לכדתניא. Lo nitzrecha
ella l’chid’tanya. Here’s what we need it for. נזכר בעל הבית ולא
נזכר שליח. Nizkar ba’al habayis v’lo nizkar shaliach. Here’s where it gets
really like wild. Michael’s there, he’s going and he’s buying the apples
and oranges, he’s doing the apples and bananas, he’s doing exactly what
I told him to do. But before he actually buys them, here
he is in the store and I think, oh my gosh, I
just sent Michael with that money that was הקדש hekdesh money. So
as soon as I realize that it’s הקדש hekdesh money and I
stop being a שוגג shogeg and I realize it, then I don’t
want him to do it anymore, but I can’t—there was no cell
phones, I couldn’t get him at the store. Okay, so he is
no longer—I don’t want him to be my שליח shaliach anymore because
I realized it was a mistake, so he’s no longer my שליח.
shaliach. And now he has transgressed, even though he’s doing exactly what
I asked him to do, even though he didn’t know. שליח מעל,
Shaliach maal, right? שליח מעל. Shaliach maal. So now the גמרא Gemara
says in a very beautiful way, שליח עניא, shaliach anya, this poor
שליח! shaliach! Michael, what did he do wrong? He did exactly what
I told him to do, he didn’t know, he was ignorant, I
woke up and I realized and now he’s מועל? moel? היינו הרים
התלויים בשערה. Hainu harim hatluyim basa’arah. That’s the mountain on a hair.
So אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, מהי קושיא? mai kushya? Why
is that difficult? דילמא מידי דהוה אמוציא מעות הקדש וכולי? Dilma midi
d’hava amotzi ma’os hekdesh v’chulei? Maybe it’s just like the normal example.
A normal example is I accidentally, if I stuck my hand in
my pocket and took the wrong money and accidentally misused הקדש hekdesh
funds, I would do מעילה, me’ilah. even though it was, oh poor
me, I didn’t know. Okay, I didn’t know, it's a שוגג, shogeg,
so fine. I don’t need to know, I made a mistake, but
I still did מעילה. me’ilah Now the obvious difference here is not
just that Michael didn’t know, but Michael had no responsibility to know,
right?
When I took the wrong money, I should have known which was
my הקדש hekdesh money and which was my non. Michael had absolutely
no responsibility, and he’s still being held liable. But the גמרא Gemara
is still saying it’s not crazy, it’s possible to transgress even in
ignorance. So אלא אמר רב אשי, Ella amar Rav Ashi, לא נצרכא
אלא כדתנן. lo nitzrecha ella k’ditnan. נטל אבן או קורה של הקדש.
Natal even o korah shel hekdesh. If somebody takes a beam or
a stone belonging to הקדש, hekdesh, הרי זה לא מעל. harei zeh
lo maal. I took it, I didn’t do מעילה. But נתנה לחברו,
nesana l’chavero, if I gave it now to Michael, here Michael, here’s
a
beam, I know
you’re building a house, I’m sure you can use this beam, הוא
מעל וחברו לא מעל. hu maal v’chavero lo maal. I was מועל
moel because by giving it to Michael I was taking it away
from הקדש. hekdesh. Michael now will not be מועל moel because once
the thing has been taken away from הקדש, hekdesh, actually an interesting
aspect of הלכות מעילה Hilchos Me’ilah is that it stops being הקדש.
hekdesh. Okay, so now the גמרא says fine, so Michael is off
either way. But מכדי, michdi, let’s take a look, says the גמרא.
משקל שקליה. Mishkal shaklei. In both cases I took the beam, right?
I took it out of הקדש’ס hekdesh's storehouse. Once I took it
out of הקדש hekdesh storehouse and brought it to my house I
haven’t done anything wrong. I give it to someone I transgress. Why
didn’t I do something wrong when I took it out of their
storehouse? מה לי הוא מה לי חברו? Ma li hu ma li
chavero? What do I care if you took it to your house
or if you gave it to your friend? Either way you took
it from הקדש. hekdesh. היינו הרים התלויים בשערה. Hainu harim hatluyim basa’arah.
That’s why it’s a mountain on a hair. Again notice, all of
these are because it doesn’t make logical sense, we’re no longer worried
about verses. And the גמרא says, מהי קושיא? mai kushya? Why is
that difficult? דילמא כשמואל, Dilma k’Shmuel, דאמר שמואל, d’amar Shmuel, הכא בגזבר
המסורות לו אבני בנין עסקינן. hacha b’gizbar hamsuros lo avnei binyan askinan.
Shmuel was so bothered with the logic of that case that he
made it a special case. And the case was I'm the temple
treasurer, I'm the temple, I'm the overseer of the beams and the
stones of הקדש. hekdesh. So as even if I'm moving them around,
wherever I'm moving them they're considered to be in הקדש’ס hekdesh's control,
right? Even if I take it to my house, which is a
funny thing, you could say, okay, you know what, sometimes you take
supplies if you're the guy in charge, you take the supplies home
and you store it so things can move around and so on.
So even though my intention might have been to steal, which is
fascinating, since in my role I am the גזבר, gizbar, there's nowhere
it can be with me that it's considered out of הקדש’ס hekdesh's
control. It's the ultimate insider embezzlement. Exactly. But on my account it
can be bit more corporate embezzlement. Exactly, there you go, exactly. דכל
היכא דמנחא ברשותא דידיה מנחא. D’chol heicha d’mancha birshusa didei mancha. Wherever
it is, it's in the הקדש’ס hekdesh's רשות. reshus. And therefore only
when I pay it out, give it to somebody else, can I
actually be seen as having taken it away from הקדש. hekdesh. So
we will continue with this tomorrow to figure out what is the
case by מעילה that doesn’t make sense that the גמרא can therefore
call הרים התלויים בשערה. harim hatluyim basa’arah. Yes, in חגיגה.